{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "After this battle's losing side fled to Trogir, the victors seized the losing kingdom’s royal seal and issued a number of fake decrees to harass one side’s leaders. A Ruthenian slave’s warning of a planned bridge crossing gave Ugrin ample time to prevent an ambush at this battle, which is sometimes named for the Sajo [[SAH-yoh]] River near which it was fought. Berke and Subotai were commanders of one army at this battle, which saw Bela the Fourth’s army annihilated by the son of Jochi. For ten points, name this main battle between the Mongols and Hungarians during the former’s invasion of Europe.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Mohi",
        "the Battle of the Tisza River",
        "the Battle of the Sajó River before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Hugh Guthrie falsely claimed that participants in this event were the first to fire in one clash. R.B. Bennett accused this event's leader, Slim Evans, of committing embezzlement. Demands for skilled laborers to receive union wages were made during this event, which was undergone by members of the Workers’ Unity League. Participants in this event fought with the Mounties in the Regina [[reh-JYE-nah]] Riot. Participants in this event often traveled in boxcars to its central city. For ten points, name this journey undertaken by Canadian laborers to protest in the national capital.",
      "answer": [
        "On-to-Ottawa Trek",
        "Regina Riot before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This scientist was the first to prove that human T-lymphotropic virus could cause cancer. This person served as the chief scientific officer of iTherX Pharmaceuticals, which produced medication for Hepatitis C. In 1990, this woman started the Center for AIDS Research at the University of California, Irvine. Passing away in 2020, for ten points, who was this Chinese-American virologist, the first researcher to clone HIV, helping prove HIV’s link to AIDS?",
      "answer": "Flossie Wong-Staal 2023 National History Bowl VJV National Championships Finals"
    },
    {
      "question": "At the Battle of Kemp’s Landing, a member of this group captured Colonel Joseph Hutchings. A member of this group, who dubbed himself “Colonel Tye,” later became the leader of the “Black Brigade,” a guerilla force tasked with defending New York City. Another member of this military unit who had previously been enslaved by George Washington participated in a rebellion in Sierra Leone. Composed of escaped enslaved persons fighting on behalf of the British Crown, for ten points, what is this military unit that originated in Virginia and disbanded in 1776?",
      "answer": [
        "Lord Dunmore’s Ethiopian Regiment",
        "Royal Ethiopian Regiment"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This group practiced male continence as a form of birth control and for their eugenicist Stirpiculture. While a member of this group, Charles Guiteau [[GEE-toh]] was referred to as “Charles Get Out” during public criticism. This group originated the term “complex marriage” and was later reorganized as a silverware company. This group was founded by John Humphrey Noyes, who preached that Jesus had returned to Earth already and that humanity needed to attain perfection in this life. For ten points, name this New York commune known for practicing free love.",
      "answer": "Oneida Community"
    },
    {
      "question": "Along the Isonzo River, this man launched four failed offensives intended to capture the fortress of Gorizia, resulting in over 250,000 casualties for his army. Following World War One, this general was heavily criticized for Italy’s defeat in the Battle of Caporetto, despite this field marshal claiming to bear no responsibility. For ten points, name this Marshal of Italy whose failed attacks during World War One earned him a reputation as one of the conflict’s worst military generals.",
      "answer": "Luigi Cadorna"
    },
    {
      "question": "Christopher Marlowe wrote an unfinished poem about this mythical figure and his lover, which would later be completed by George Chapman. Following his successful emulation of a notable feat of this mythical figure, Lord Byron composed the poem “Written After Swimming from Sestos to Abydos.” This figure convinced his lover, a priestess of Aphrodite, that a virgin was not suited for such a position. For ten points, name this figure, who drowned after his lover Hero plunged to her death in the sea.",
      "answer": [
        "Leander",
        "Hero and Leander"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of this event's leaders stated that \"Nothing is lost, save honor.\" One of the men who caused this event was Abel Corbin, who married a sister of the sitting president. Robber barons sought knowledge about the sale of the central good during this event, four million dollars of which was released on September 24, 1869. Insights into Ulysses Grant's policies were sought in the lead-up to, for ten points, what event in which Jim Fisk and Jay Gould attempted to corner the market on gold?",
      "answer": "Black Friday gold panic 2023 National History Bowl VJV National Championships Finals"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler was the subject of a prophecy by Savonarola, who claimed he was God’s instrument to purify the corruption of Florence. This ruler challenged the authority of Maximilian the First to establish a personal union with Brittany, and was pushed to stop supporting Perkin Warbeck by Henry the Seventh. This king pursued his loose claim to the throne of Naples by marching his army up and down a certain peninsula before being challenged at the Fornovo. For ten points, name this “Affable” King of France who launched the Italian Wars.",
      "answer": [
        "Charles the Eighth of France",
        "Charles the Affable",
        "Charles l’Affable before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Newton D. Baker headed a board that exonerated Herbert Jermain Slocum for his inability to prevent this event, which allegedly resulted in one side obtaining 80 horses and 300 rifles. The 13th Cavalry Regiment was deployed in the aftermath of this event, which sparked the Punitive Expedition into its leader's country. The Division of the North undertook this action in a town three miles north of the border with Mexico. For ten points, identify this 1916 attack carried out by Pancho Villa in a New Mexico town.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Columbus",
        "Burning of Columbus",
        "Pancho Villa's Columbus Raid",
        "Raid on Columbus"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During a Congressional debate over the Voting Rights Act of 1965, this man told Senator Jacob Javits, the only Jewish member of the higher chamber, “I don’t like you — or your kind.” This politician told President Lyndon B. Johnson, “I believe it’s a publicity stunt,” regarding the murder of three civil rights workers in his home state. Joe Biden faced criticism in 2019 for saying that this segregationist senator “never called me ‘boy,’ he always called me ‘son.’\" For ten points, name this “Voice of the White South,” a U.S. senator from Mississippi.",
        "answer": "James Oliver Eastland or Jim Eastland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Eastland served alongside this other Mississippi senator and white supremacist whose noted hearing-loss led Richard Nixon to propose a namesake “compromise” in which he would listen to the Watergate tapes and make comparisons to the transcript.",
        "answer": "John Cornelius Stennis 2023 National History Bowl VJV National Championships Finals"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler’s minority was dominated by several German captains, beginning with Markward von Anweiler. The assassination of Philip of Swabia by Count Otto the Eighth opened the way for this ruler’s accession to the imperial throne. This ruler negotiated the return of Jerusalem to Christian hands despite being excommunicated during the Sixth Crusade. Called “Stupor Mundi,” or “the wonder of the world,” and “the First European” by Friedrich Nietzsche, for ten points, name this Holy Roman Emperor who was widely considered the ideal “Renaissance Man.”",
        "answer": [
          "Frederick the Second, Holy Roman Emperor",
          "“Friedrich”",
          "“Federico”",
          "“Fridericus” in place of “Frederick”"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This conflict arose between Frederick and the Papacy, seeing fighting in central and southern Italy before the Treaty of San Germano secured the status quo.",
        "answer": "War of the Keys"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An item designed by this man's company hid Grace Kelly's \"baby bump\" in a 1956 photograph which made it onto the cover of Life. In 2014, Axel Dumas [[doo-MAH]] became CEO of the company founded by this man, who relied on a hand-made stitching technique to manufacture horse harnesses. In 1984, the company this man founded developed a bag line named after the actress Jane Birkin. Born in a French-controlled German region in 1801, for ten points, who was this founder of a French fashion house?",
        "answer": [
          "Thierry Hermès ]",
          "phonetic pronunciations",
          "Hermès International S.A."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2003, Hermès named this French fashion designer as its creative director. This unconventional \"enfant terrible\" designed Madonna's \"cone bra\" and, in 2012, became the first fashion designer to sit on the Jury for the Main Competition at Cannes.",
        "answer": [
          "Jean Paul Gaultier ]",
          "phonetic pronunciations"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This paper was the only major publication to defend suspected serial killer John Bodkin Adams. This pro-Brexit paper notably published front-page conspiracy theories regarding the death of Princess Diana on the one-year anniversary of the London bombings. Despite its association with a Canada-born British politician who was involved in the ousting of H.H. Asquith, this paper was founded in 1900 by Arthur Pearson. This paper became the world’s most circulated under the leadership of Lord Beaverbrook. For ten points, name this popular London-based tabloid newspaper.",
        "answer": "Daily Express"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Daily Express was run from this street, which provides the workplace of a character in a 1973 play by Christopher Bond.",
        "answer": "Fleet Street 2023 National History Bowl VJV National Championships Finals"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An essay about this location borrows a term from Jeremy Bentham to describe a game whose stakes are so extreme that it is irrational to participate. A short film titled Trance and Dance in this place depicted local women engaging in a ritual dance with kris daggers. This place was ruled by a “Theater State” according to the book Negara, and this location is the subject of the essay “Deep Play.” For ten points, name this Indonesian island where Clifford Geertz observed cockfights.",
        "answer": "Bali"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This anthropologist collaborated with his wife Margaret Mead on studies published in Balinese Character. This man also wrote Steps to an Ecology of Mind.",
        "answer": "Gregory Bateson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Seventh Letter provides advice to this man’s uncle's followers on how to advise and contain this man. This man conspired with Philistus to have his uncle, Dion, exiled and give away his property and wife to his rivals. This man’s lavish lifestyle prompted his uncle to bring Plato to teach him. According to legend, this man demonstrated the dangers of being in power by using horsehair to hang a sword over the head of Damocles. For ten points, name this 4th century BC Sicilian Tyrant.",
        "answer": "Dionysius the Second of Syracuse or Dionysius the Younger"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Dionysius’s reign came to an end with the invasion of this Corinthian ruler, who established democracy in Syracuse.",
        "answer": "Timoleon of Corinth"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man once wrote a \"Poem About [mean word]s\" in which he fussed about other people giving him instructions. This man complained about a sky god with his name and threatened to fire cannons at that god's mother due to a lack of rain. This man was also known as “72-Cannon” and the \"man of three-don't-knows.\" This man numbered his many Russian mistresses because he forgot their names. Called “China’s basest warlord” by Times, for ten points, name this “dogmeat general” who served as military governor of Shandong.",
        "answer": "Zhang Zongchang"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As his army fell apart, Zhang sought Japanese protection in this city, home to the former Russian base of Port Arthur.",
        "answer": "Dalian 2023 National History Bowl VJV National Championships Finals"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After conquering the people who built it, this kingdom relied on the Marib Dam for its water supply. After his son was killed, a ruler of this kingdom cut down every palm tree in Yathrib to deny them their livelihood. This kingdom was ruled by the Jewish dynasty of Dhu Nuwas, and was ended after being invaded and annexed by Ethiopia’s Aksum Empire. This kingdom’s capital was located at Zafar, near the modern city of Sana’a. For ten points, name this ancient kingdom based in Yemen.",
        "answer": [
          "Himyarite Kingdom or Homerite Kingdom",
          "or Mamlakat Ḥimyar"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Himyarite Kingdom conquered these South Arabian people, who are listed alongside Jews and Christians in the Qur'an as People of the Book and who may be related to the Mandaeans.",
        "answer": "Sabaeans"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After Pope Hadrian the Third died on his way to Worms [[VURMS]], this man was unable to convince his bishops to recognize his illegitimate son Bernard as his heir. After being forced to pay tribute, this king called a conference at Spijk [[SPAYK]], where his men ambushed and killed Godfrid and blinded Hugh. After this man was deposed by his nephew, the Carolingian Empire dissolved into West, Middle, and East Francia. For ten points, name this often-mocked Germanic king, the son of Louis the German, who twice bribed Viking raiders to stop their invasions.",
        "answer": "Charles the Fat or Charles the Third"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Charles the Fat’s nephew who deposed him, named Arnulf, was a duke of which region, located mostly today in southern Austria and historically containing portions of northern Slovenia?",
        "answer": "Carinthia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Though not Hungarian himself, this artist fled the Iron Curtain in 1956 due to the Hungarian Uprising, and then spent 17 years as a stateless person before becoming a US citizen. One work by this artist closed early after a woman was killed by an umbrella while visiting it. This artist, together with his Moroccan-born partner, who died in 2009, was known for installations such as The London Mastaba and The Floating Piers, as well as a project in Biscayne Bay that involved the use of pink fabric. For ten points, name this artist who worked with Jeanne-Claude to wrap the Reichstag.",
        "answer": "Christo 2023 National History Bowl VJV National Championships Finals"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another Christo and Jeanne-Claude project was wrapping this bridge in Paris in 1985. With its construction beginning in 1578, it is the oldest bridge over the Seine still standing in Paris, its name notwithstanding.",
        "answer": "Pont Neuf"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Regarding the state of Missouri, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding the state of missouri, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Only president from Missouri, who succeeded FDR.",
          "answer": "Harry S. Truman"
        },
        {
          "question": "General nicknamed who commanded the American Expeditionary Force during World War One.",
          "answer": "John Joseph \"Black Jack\" Pershing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Newsman and Saint Joseph native nicknamed the “Most Trusted Man in America\" as anchorman for CBS Evening News.",
          "answer": "Walter Cronkite or Walter Leland Cronkite, Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "St. Louis University attended by Tennessee Williams and conservative activist Phyllis Schlafly.",
          "answer": [
            "Washington University in St. Louis",
            "WashU",
            "WUSTL"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Serenity Prayer\" author whom Time Magazine called the “greatest Protestant theologian in America since Jonathan Edwards.\"",
          "answer": "Reinhold Niebuhr or John Paul Reinhold Niebuhr"
        },
        {
          "question": "Democratic political machine boss convicted of tax evasion and prosecuted by US attorney Maurice Milligan.",
          "answer": "Tom Pendergast or Thomas Joseph \"T.J.\" Pendergast"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Black man to serve a full term in the U.S. Senate.",
          "answer": "Blanche Bruce or Blanche Kelso Bruce"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cultural region of Central Missouri, coinciding with “Little Dixie,” which historically connected the east coast to the Oregon and California Trails.",
          "answer": [
            "Boonslick or Boone’s Lick Country",
            "or Boone’s Lick Road"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The ancient Colline Gate was...",
      "prompt": "Name the the ancient colline gate was......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Located at the foot of the Quirinal Hill in what Italian city which governed a classical European empire?",
          "answer": [
            "Rome",
            "Roman Empire"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Adjacent to baths named for what emperor, who persecuted Christians and established the Tetrarchy?",
          "answer": "Diocletian or Gaius Aurelius Valerius Diocletianus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Above the place where what women, who tended a sacred fire, were buried alive if they broke their vow of chastity?",
          "answer": "Vestal Virgins or Vestales"
        },
        {
          "question": "Near the temple of what goddess, the personification of luck?",
          "answer": "Fortuna"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of the decisive loss for what populares [[poh-poo-LAH-rehs]] leader and seven-time consul?",
          "answer": "Gaius Marius"
        },
        {
          "question": "Legendarily built by what sixth king, who ruled between the Tarquins and names the walls its part of?",
          "answer": [
            "Servius Tullius",
            "either underlined portion",
            "Servian Wall"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Adjacent on the other side to gardens named for what historian, who wrote The Catiline Conspiracy?",
          "answer": "Sallust or Gaius Sallustius Crispus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was directly east of what large public space that was originally the site of seasonal musters prior to armies marching off to war.",
          "answer": [
            "Campus Martius or Field of Mars",
            "or Campo Marzio"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding the Red River Rebellion, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding the red river rebellion, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country in which the rebellion occurred.",
          "answer": "Canada"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern province, once comprising the majority of Rupert's Land, at the center of the rebellion.",
          "answer": "Manitoba"
        },
        {
          "question": "Language spoken by most Métis [[MEH-tee]], whom the rebellion sought to protect.",
          "answer": "French"
        },
        {
          "question": "Company whose transfer of Rupert’s Land to Canada paved the way for the rebellion.",
          "answer": [
            "Hudson’s Bay Company",
            "HBC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Métis leader who fled at the end of the rebellion.",
          "answer": "Louis Riel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future British commander-in-chief who led the expedition sent to secure sovereignty after the rebellion.",
          "answer": [
            "Garnet Wolseley or Garnet Joseph Wolseley",
            "or 1st Viscount Wolseley",
            "Wolseley expedition"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Lieutenant governor whose actions led to the creation of the provisional government.",
          "answer": "William McDougall"
        },
        {
          "question": "Irish settler who killed Norbert Parisien and was himself controversially executed by the rebels.",
          "answer": "Thomas Scott"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This officer led an ambush that captured the Union steamboat J. R. Williams in what is referred to as the only naval battle in Oklahoma. While this officer remained loyal to the Confederacy, his rival John (20 pts)",
        "Ross returned to the Union side, splitting their nation in two. Early in the Civil War, this officer took over the First (10 pts)",
        "Cherokee Mounted Rifles from John Drew. For ten points, name this officer, the only Native American general of the Civil War and the last Confederate general to surrender."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Stand Watie",
        "Standhope Uwatie",
        "Tawkertawker",
        "Isaac S. Watie",
        "Degataga"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One member of this family gifted a grain dropped by a bird to Miyan Bhoiya, whose harvest from the grain helped him fund the Lentil Mosque. The Shisha Gumbad was constructed by members of this dynasty and can be found in its namesake (20 pts)",
        "Gardens. One member of this family was thought to have amassed over 100,000 men and nearly 100 elephants at a battle in which a king of Kabulistan used artillery to overcome the larger force. Sikander was a member of this dynasty, another of whose members was defeated at (10 pts)",
        "Panipat by Babur. For ten points, name this family of Delhi sultans that included Ibrahim."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Lodi",
        "Ibrahim Lodi",
        "Sikandar Lodi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Celery-like leaves ornament the exterior of this building, which was named for a local brewer. Built after the completion of its architect’s Auditorium Building, this building was said to evoke the (20 pts)",
        "“vivid image of powerful upward movement.” This building, which displays an intricate leaf-like frieze around bulls-eye windows near its top, exemplifies its architect's maxim, (10 pts)",
        "“form follows function.” Created with the assistance of Dankmar Adler, this terra cotta building was once referred to as the “Taj Mahal of St. Louis.” For ten points, name this early skyscraper designed by Louis Sullivan."
      ],
      "answer": "Wainwright Building"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A bishop of this city who fled after Charlemagne’s campaign against the Saxons was named Willehad [[VIL-luh-hahd]]. A native of this city wrote a set of Deeds of Bishops of the Hamburg Church. Four “Outcast animals” who flee their abusive masters eventually become musicians in this city in a tale by the (20 pts)",
        "Brothers Grimm. This largest city on the River Weser [[VEH-zuh]] was home to a chronicler whose description of Vinland was the first known written account of the New World. That man was named \"Adam of [this city].” Located near, but not being a part of, a Swedish duchy alongside Verden, (10 pts)",
        "for ten points, what is this city, the capital and namesake of the smallest and least populous state in Germany?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Bremen or Breem",
        "or Bremer",
        "Stadtgemeinde Bremen",
        "The Bremen Town Musicians",
        "Die Bremer Stadtmusikanten",
        "Adam of Bremen 2023 National History Bowl VJV National Championships Finals"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After a race in Taunton in which this man placed second, the third-place finisher William Becker choked this man to unconsciousness. Theodore Roosevelt was a supporter of this athlete, who was nicknamed the \"Worcester Whirlwind.\" The (20 pts)",
        "exhumation and movement of the remains of this man were overseen by Frank Schwinn. A velodrome in Indianapolis is named after this man, who won an (10 pts)",
        "1899 one-mile sprint competition in Montreal. Sometimes prevented from competing in whites- only races, for ten points, who was this world-champion African-American cyclist?"
      ],
      "answer": "Major Taylor or Marshall Walter \"Major\" Taylor"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this conflict, one king ordered destruction so massive that it would cause “a perpetual memory of the vengeance of God lightened upon [one side] for their falsehood and disloyalty.\" The Battle of Solway Moss occurred during this conflict, during which the (20 pts)",
        "Auld Alliance was purposefully broken. This conflict was partly caused by the renunciation of a marriage agreement between a member of the House of Stuart and a son of Jane Seymour. The Treaty of (10 pts)",
        "Greenwich ended this conflict, which lasted from 1543 to 1551. For ten points, name this conflict between a Franco-Scottish alliance and Henry the Eighth."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "War of the Rough Wooing",
        "the Eight Years' War before the years are read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) At this battle, a forest known as the Wood of Barry stood in front of the left flank of the winning side. Vezon and Bourgeon were key locations at this battle, which was the subject of a commemorative poem by Voltaire. Fought in the (20 pts)",
        "Antoing municipality near Tournai, this battle saw a failed charge of 15,000 troops partly led by the Duke of Cumberland. This battle in the Habsburg Netherlands brought fame to (10 pts)",
        "Maurice de Saxe, though his side was forced to concede their gains in the Treaty of Aix-La-Chapelle. For ten points, name this major French victory in the War of the Austrian Succession."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Fontenoy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these people named Louis Henri [[loo-EE ahn-REE]] supposedly visited the royal courts of Europe, including that of Louis the Thirteenth, in an account by the monk Claude d'Abbeville. Upon European arrival, these people allowed Portuguese men to practice polygamy in a process known as (20 pts)",
        "cunhadismo [[coon-hah-DEES- moh]], which translates to “Brother-in-Law.” These speakers of Nheengatu [[heen- GAH-too]] were made famous by Hans Staden, who supposedly survived these people’s (10 pts)",
        "ritual of cannibalism by curing a local chief. For ten points, name these indigenous people of Brazil who inhabited the Amazon jungle."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Tupi",
        "Tupinamba 2023 National History Bowl VJV National Championships Finals"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this work, the author notes that one place \"is too extensive to sleep all at once, and too watchful, even in its slumbers \" The lines \"Universal empire is the prerogative of a writer\" appear in this work, whose author wrote of his time at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Fort Lee in New Jersey. The line \"these are the times that try men's souls\" was originally found in this series, whose first (10 pts)",
        "pamphlet was published in the Pennsylvania Journal in 1776. Written under the pseudonym \"Common Sense,\" for ten points, what was this series of pamphlets that Thomas Paine wrote during the Revolutionary War?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Crisis",
        "The American Crisis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man has been posthumously criticized for bringing Minik Wallace and his Inuit family to live in the American Museum of Natural History. This man’s theories on societal development have been encompassed into the general theory of Historical (20 pts)",
        "Particularism. This man, who studied the Bella Coola people, also studied the Kwakiutl and their potlatch ceremonies. This man’s students included Alfred Kroeber and (10 pts)",
        "Margaret Mead. Establishing a department at Columbia University, for ten points, name this man who is considered the “Father of American Anthropology.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Franz Boas 2023 National History Bowl VJV National Championships Finals"
    }
  ]
}